I'll be pretty quick here. Um, obviously
super excited to get Vang in here and
and uh be able to welcome him and his
family to uh the Ravens family and and
what was really clear, you know,
obviously we get to spend time with a
lot of different prospects in this this
process. Um, but when he got to come in
here and and we got to spend some time
with him, it was very clear that uh he
was a Raven and and what that meant, I
mean, what that means to us is really um
he embodies, you know, the idea, the
values, all the things that uh we're
looking to uh put into place here with
Jesse and in the new regime. And um it
was very clear to us that he would make
a great uh addition to the the roster
and be able to come in here. You know,
he's he's a humble guy um that competes.
He he shows it all over the tape and uh
I'm certainly very excited to to be able
to coach him and and uh him join us on
on this uh journey here.
>> Uh any questions for for either of us?
>> Uh you know, welcome to uh Baltimore. Uh
uh I we sort of asked you yesterday a
little bit. How much you know because
you'll be blocking in front of Lamar,
how much have you kind of admired him
from afar? And you know, so you know,
now a day since you've been drafted,
have you kind of thought about the the
possibility of, you know, blocking for
him as well?
>> Oh man, I thought about it a lot. You
know, his name is a big name around the
game. He's been around the game for a
little while now. He's a very talented
player, phenomenal player. You know,
it's going to be a big honor for me and
a blessing for me to, you know, block
for somebody like that. So, taking a lot
of pride in that.
>> Um, you brought up the, um, Alo
aircraft, the Ali Natada, um,
comparison. You said you've heard that
before. Just curious, how familiar are
you with him and and what does that kind
of mean to you when you hear that?
>> I'm familiar with his game. Um heard his
name growing up, you know, watched a
little bit of ball. His name was always
around, you know, but being compared to
somebody like that, it's not something
to take lightly. You know, he's a great
player. He's done a lot for the game
himself. So, you know, to be compared to
somebody like that means a lot to me.
D, have you been able to kind of catch
up to how fast pace it's probably been
for you over the last 12 hours or so?
>> Uh, not really. Uh, been a long day
yesterday. Got about like 4 hours of
sleep last night. Now we're here, but
you know, all of it's a blessing. Know
God has a plan for all of us, you know,
just a part of it. You know, take not
taking it lightly, but it's part of the
process.
>> How much uh do you know about the Ravens
and their I know you've been asked a
bunch of questions, but how familiar are
you at? How much have you followed the
team growing up?
>> Um, I mean, I know the basics, you know,
there's a lot of history, a lot of, you
know, legends that came came through
here. A lot of big names, know, a lot
of, um, you know, legends that have left
a big part of themselves into this
facility, you know, a lot of this this
game. So, it means a lot to me that I'm
here now.
>> Hey, Dean. Uh, something that Jesse
mentioned last night is that the bank is
really sche versatile and can fit in
multiple different uh, schemes. How big
of a factor was that during the
evaluation process that made you want to
to try to get in?
>> That's a huge factor. I mean, obviously,
um the versatility that he has in his
game, it allows you on offense to be
very multiple and um you know, really he
can do a lot of different things and and
you always want to be building the
scheme around the player. Um and because
of his unique skill set, it allows you
to uh be able to try to stress defenses
in a lot of different ways.
Exactly. What we heard a little bit
about it, but what was Coach Leford like
to be around last night when the fake
came in and how much did he push for
this?
>> So, like you you got to see the video of
um you know, Eric being able to talk and
Jesse being able to talk. You couldn't
see Coach Led walk into the room and
just like jumping out of his seat like
ready to explode. So, um Coach Leadford
was so fired up from the very beginning.
Um, you know, we really identified Vanga
as a guy that really we really felt like
would uh add to our offense and um he's
been beating that drum for for weeks
now. Um, for it to be able to come to
fruition and you know him to be sitting
there when we were picking um it was it
was really just uh awesome for for all
sides.
>> And can you talk about your relationship
already that you're starting to build
with coach Leadford and I I know he was
working you out at your pro day and kind
of how how that all went with him.
>> Yeah, that was the first time I met him.
you know, he's explaining the drills and
then I had a rep like I'm up taking a
knee about to run outside zone. He goes,
"I'mma hold a bag." I was like, "All
right, I'm going to use that to my
advantage." You know, I'm trying to push
him on his ass a little bit, you know,
and then after the entire, you know,
we're done with proday, he comes up.
He's like, you almost put me on my ass.
I was like, you know, trying to play it
off like I didn't know I was trying to
do that. So, but, you know, that's my
guys. This is how the game works, you
know? So,
>> thank you. There's always going to be
some people who say, "How do you take a
guard in the first round, right? Why why
don't you take a pass rusher or what
have you. What if anything would you say
to those people?
>> There's, you know, 11 people on the
field at the same time. You're missing
one. You can't play a game of football.
You can't play real football without O
linemen. And if you don't have a
complete five, there's five people up
front that play as one. There's a lot of
pride that needs to be taken upon that.
So for me getting picked first round to
play as a guard, take a lot of pride in
that. coming in. I'm trying to, you
know, make a big impact playing as a
guard, just proving them wrong.
>> Thing after you heard your name called
and got drafted, what is kind of the
coolest and most memorable thing that
happened since? Was it a moment you
share with your family? Was it a phone
call you got? What would you say was the
kind of the one thing that really stuck
out since you got drafted?
>> Um, I say two big moments. When I put
the hat on my dad, he didn't take it off
for the next like two hours. He left the
hat on the entire time. And after that,
we took a picture as a whole family. You
know, I got eight siblings. I'm the
ninth and youngest one. We're all
standing there, you know, nice little
view in the back. It's my entire family.
That's my whole reason of being here,
making it this far. You know, those
people are my my why. Like I said
before, you know, I did this for them.
And seeing that come to fruition, like
you said, that's that's a big part to
me.
>> Then as you're growing up and developing
and, you know, the possibility of being
an NFL player comes into focus. Who were
some offensive linemen and some players
that maybe you watched, you studied,
that you modeled yourself after that
made an impression on you?
>> I was a big Quentyn Nelson fan. Watched
a lot of his film, a lot of Zion Johnson
film. Um, I say Peter from Titans, the
Titans as well, a lot of those film and
uh Trent Williams, I watch a lot of his
film as well. He's I know he's a tackle,
but he plays real well.
>> And I know you were a rugby player
growing up predominantly. When was it
that you kind of fell in love with
football? Can you tell us the story or
the moment that you kind of realized it?
>> I mean, I watched a lot of football
growing up. My older brothers, they w or
they play football high school and all
that. And I was a young kid watching
them play on the islands and, you know,
didn't really not much came from that
with them. But, you know, from then on,
I knew the game was a big part of our
family, our culture, things like that.
Came to Washington State, you know, my
mom said no football, no nothing like
that. Focus on school. She's right here,
but you know, she loves football now and
that's all that matters to me.
>> When Jesse said yesterday that you guys
still don't really know yet how the
guard configuration is going to work
out, what is that figuring out process
look like to you?
>> Yeah, I mean really with the offensive
line always, it's how do we get up five
best on the field? Um obviously he's got
a lot of versatility and and that allows
us to really um go out and try to
explore that through the offseason,
through training camp and uh really make
it a competitive environment that um you
know our guys are able to kind of
showcase their skill sets where we think
they're going to fit our offense best um
and be able to make that decision you
know later on into camp. But um
certainly guys like this that have you
know a lot of different they've played a
lot of different places. Um, I mean,
I've seen him flexed out as a tight end
at times and slicing back and and, um,
you know, knocking out an end on the
other side. And so, um, guys like that
allow you to, uh, really explore, you
know, what is the best fit for our our
best five.
>> Have you found that guys earlier in
their career are typically more flexible
when it comes to moving from the left
side to the right side and vice versa?
>> I would say, yeah, I mean, just muscle
memory for anybody, um, the more reps
you take on anything, the more
comfortable you get there. And um so you
know really a transition time like this
where he's coming from uh college to pro
you know that is uh it's a really good
time to to make that change if you're if
you're moving around.
>> One of the stats that kind of jump out
about him that you know hasn't allowed a
sack the last two years at Penn State
you know and watching him. What makes
him so good as a pass protector?
>> Uh reactive athleticism is um of a very
very strong trait. He's great with his
hands. um he does a great job of of
starting the fight in in the rush. Um I
think there's a a lot of different
reasons that uh that stat comes out.
It's not one one area of his game.
There's a lot of areas of his game where
uh he does a great job of controlling
the depth of the pocket and being able
to uh you know handle whether that's a
guy playing outside of him or or a guy
playing in the A gap. Um he does he does
a great job in protection.
>> Um when you got the call and heard it
was the Ravens, what was the first thing
that came to mind? And since then, have
you had any uh current Ravens reach out
to you?
>> Um, no current Ravens reach out yet. You
know, I'm expecting it, but you know, I
was talking to EDC before I left. He
goes, like right before I'm walking out
the building, he goes, "When you get
that call with that uh area code, you
know, it's going to be us." My phone's
sitting there, I see the area code pop
up. You know, I just felt a whole, you
know, feeling of relief. You know,
everything just flushed out and I
relaxed a little bit knowing that that
moment was everything that I've been
working for. I got the call, answered
it, I said, "What's up, big dog?" We're
ready to go. You know, things like that.
But I was real happy that I'm here now.
Ben,
>> I was reading uh maybe a year or two
ago, you dropped about 20 pounds going
into a season. Uh what did that do for
your game? And do you consider maybe
like your athleticism as well as your
strength to be, you know, one of one of
your strengths?
>> Uh for me, it definitely improved my
level of play. um felt like I was moving
a lot quicker, coming off the ball more,
just being lighter. But the whole losing
weight thing, it was more of just a me
decision. After the season, my junior
season, I was like, "Let me see what 325
feels like." Personally, I didn't feel
like I lost any power or anything like
that. But, you know, my old line coach
is saying that I'm moving a lot better.
You know, just playing ball better. So,
>> good. What um what's your earliest I
know you said you grew up, you know, go
out and see watching your older brothers
play. What's your earliest just general
football memory and what app kind of
appealed to you?
>> Um, I say 10th grade. Got my first start
on varsity. I'm playing left tackle.
We're playing a team from Oregon. You
know, he's he's like six. I've never
seen somebody that big. You know, he's
coming off the ball. He beats me off the
edge and I'm grabbing him and I'm
pulling it back as he's beating me off
the edge. I had no idea what I was
doing, but got a flag caught on me, but
you know, that's how it was.
Hey, what's the uh best worst
pronunciation you've heard of in your
name?
>> Oh man. Um,
for some reason I don't understand where
people get the L from in my last name.
They spell with an L, but somebody
spelled my name Oliva Vanga or something
like that. Y oron. It's no good, but I
hope you would get it now. So,
>> I remember there's an interview that you
said you learned pretty quick how to be
physical when going up against uh Penn
State defensive lineman and pass
rushers. Was it Diesa Isaac one of them
or does it mean to be teammates with him
now?
>> Diesa Isaac back then, you know, we had
crazy different packages on defense and
I was like a two at the time. You know,
he's lined up at the four eye and his
get off is insane. Like he was he was an
athlete back then. He still is now. with
his his like hand grip. I remember
punching him one time. He grabs my hand
with like barely any effort into it and
just rips it off of him. He like beats
me off that I get ripped by my line
coach. So that's how it was going
against him.
>> There was a story when you were in
college about you used to print out
pictures and sticky notes of other
teams, guys, and put them on your
bedroom wall just to remind you. Where
did that start? Where did that come
from? How did that help? And is that
something you might try to do in the
NFL? Uh for me it was a lot of like
changing my process of how I get ready
for a game. Um that started like late
junior season. It was more of a thing
reminding me that that's the goal of the
entire week. You know, reminding myself
that these are the guys I'm going
against, you know, drilling in my head,
you know, what they do, how they play,
things like that. But it's all part of
the process of getting ready for the
next game.
>> People who review your film talk about
just the consistency of the pass block
reps. I mean, the the efficiency of the
movement, the the lack of penalties, all
that kind of when when did you and how
did you sort of become that technician?
>> Um, it's a big shout out to my O line
coach. You know, that was one thing he
harped on a lot was being detailed as an
O lineman. It was either being detailed
in the meeting room or out on the field.
It's all the focusing on, you know,
technique stuff, getting your hands here
rather than there, things like that.
Getting your your foot there on in the
run game. But now, I focus a lot on the
little details rather than the big
things. So,
>> can you uh I guess take us through the
process of of getting that suit and what
what it means to you?
>> I just wanted to keep it simple and the
lapel is just like part of our culture,
you know, get a little tribal on there,
but nothing much to it.
>> Yesterday, you talked about kind of how
you flipped that switch from off the
field to on the field instead. It took
you a while to kind of perfect that. Was
that, you know, kind of ramping yourself
up into that intensity and that mindset?
like can you talk about that process of
kind of be building that that flip of
the switch?
>> Uh for me pregame I'm going in, you
know, calm. You can't do nothing full
speed when you're, you know, all all
antsy and things like that. So I'm all
calm during the game or before the game.
As soon as the game starts, you know,
I'm a different person. I'm trying to
kill somebody. But, you know, it's all
staying calm and then when you see me
play on the field, it's it's calm as
well. But the mentality of just talking
smack, things like that. No, I'm
confident in my preparation, knowing
what's going on before it happens.
That's why I play like that.
>> Bang. You talk to your um your old
quarterback Josh. You told me about
story about you guys playing that game
against Collins Hill and the bus being
surrounded and you kind of standing up
and and and you know saying I got this
and taking everybody off. What do you
remember about that moment? What kind of
prompted you to to be the guy in that
situation? I mean, not much to it, you
know, just showing up, you know, being
the guys that do the things that nobody
else wants to do. I take a lot of pride
in that. Um, you know, I was one of
those guys that everybody looked up to.
But, you know, I'm never a guy that
speaks before, you know, things need to
be said, but, you know, when things need
to be said, I'll definitely be the guy
to do it.
>> Man, if somebody ask you what's the best
and the worst part of growing up being
the youngest of nine, what would you
say? Um,
excuse my language, but they used to
beat my ass all the time. That's that's
how bad it got. But, you know, they they
roughed me up a little bit growing up,
but that's just how the household was.
You know, like I said, I wouldn't be
here if it wasn't for them. So,
>> are you the biggest now?
>> No.
>> Yeah. I got brothers that are bigger
than me. So,
>> yeah.
>> All right. All right. Thank you. It was
coming.